## CHINMAY KULKARNI

chinmayk@cs.cmu.edu · (412) 268-5831 5000 Forbes Avenue Pittsburgh, PA 15213

My research asks the question: how do we create lifelong learning opportunities for millions of people? And how do we do so in ways that combine formal learning with intellectual development in new forms of work? So far, it has yielded systems for large-scale peer assessment and discussion that have been used by more than 100,000 students in over a hundred Massive Open Online Classrooms (MOOCs). In continuing work, my research group is investigating how new forms of work can be designed around learning.

#### **EMPLOYMENT** Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA

2015 - current

Assistant Professor, Human-computer Interaction Institute

School of Computer Science

#### **EDUCATION** Stanford University, Stanford, CA

2010 - 2015

Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science

Advisors: Scott Klemmer and Michael Bernstein

BITS Pilani, Pilani, India

2005 - 2009

Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science

#### **FUNDING** Awarded:

Office of Naval Research

Provably Impartial Peer Assessment for Expert Hiring

Principal Investigator

\$400,000

(Co-PI: Ariel Procaccia, CSD)

Manufacturing Futures Initiative at Carnegie Mellon

VirtualCellLab: Accelerating tacit knowledge in cell-culture manufacturing

Principal Investigator

\$197,000

(Co-PI: Rebecca Taylor, CIT)

Department of Education/IES

PDConnect: A Scalable Community Approach to Improving Instruction in AP Chem-

istry Nationwide

coPrincipal Investigator (under sub-contract with Stony Brook University) \$1,800,000

#### **PATENTS** Identifying Topically-related Phrases In A Browsing Sequence

US 8,655,648 B2

Framework that facilitates third party integration of applications into a

search engine

US 20120166276 A1; pending

#### CONSULTING Eloquent Labs (eloquent.ai)

Aug 2016-present

Advice on creating scalable systems for combining human and machine intelligence

for open-domain customer tasks.

### PeerStudio, Inc. (peerstudio.org)

May 2018-present

Founder and technical advisor. My hopefully-sustainable small business (not a startup) creates opportunities for peer learning for individuals and small businesses.

# AWARDS & HONORS

Arthur Samuel Thesis Award, 2015-2016

Siebel Scholar, 2014

Doctoral Consortium, UIST 2014 Google Influential Paper Award 2014

Facebook Graduate Fellowship Finalist, 2013

Best Paper Award: Eurovis 2013

### JOURNAL ARTICLES

Peer and Self Assessment in Massive Online Classes; Chinmay Kulkarni, Wei, K. P., Le H., Chia D., Papadopoulos K., Cheng J., Koller D, Scott Klemmer; in *TOCHI: ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction*, Vol 20, Issue 6 (2013)

## PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS

Julia Cambre, Scott Klemmer, Chinmay Kulkarni. 2018. Juxtapeer: Comparative Peer Review Yields Higher Quality Feedback and Promotes Deeper Reflection. *Proceedings of CHI* (2018).

Anson Kahng, Yasmine Kotturi, Chinmay Kulkarni, David Kurokawa, Ariel D. Procaccia. 2018. Ranking Wily People Who Rank Each Other. *Proceedings of AAAI* (2018).

Rebecca M. Quintana, Christopher Brooks, Cinzia Smothers, Yuanru Tan, Zheng Yao, Chinmay Kulkarni. 2018 Mentor Academy: Engaging Global Learners in the Creation of Data Science Problems for MOOCs. *Proceedings of the International Conference of Learning Sciences*, 2018

Adam Stankiewicz, Chinmay Kulkarni. 2016. \$1 Conversational Turn Detector. Proceedings of ACM Learning at Scale (2016), March, 2016.

Chinmay Kulkarni, Michael Bernstein, Scott Klemmer. 2015. PeerStudio: Rapid peer feedback emphasizes iteration and improves performance. *Proceedings of ACM Learning at Scale (2015), March, 2015.* 

Yasmine Kotturi, Michael Bernstein, Chinmay Kulkarni, Scott Klemmer. 2015. Structure and messaging techniques for online peer learning systems that increase stickiness. *Proceedings of ACM Learning at Scale (2015), March, 2015.* 

Chinmay Kulkarni, Julia Cambre, Yasmine Kotturi, Michael Bernstein, Scott Klemmer. 2015. Talkabout: Making Distance Matter with Small Groups in Massive Classes. Proceedings of CSCW: ACM Conference on Computer Supported Collaborative Work (2015), March, 2015.

Chinmay Kulkarni, Socher, R., Michael Bernstein, Scott Klemmer. 2014. The identify-verify pattern: combining peer assessment with algorithmic scoring to scale short-answer grading. *Proceedings of ACM Learning at Scale (2014)*, March, 2014.

Lin S., Fortuna J., Chinmay Kulkarni, Maureen Stone, Jeffrey Heer. 2013. Selecting Semantically-Resonant Colors for Data Visualization. *Proceedings of Eurographics Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) 2013.* Best Paper Award

Chinmay Kulkarni, Ed H. Chi. 2013. All the News thats Fit to Read: A Study

of Social Annotations for News Reading. Proceedings of CHI: ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (2013). Google Influential Paper 2013

Chinmay Kulkarni, Steven Dow, Scott Klemmer. 2012. Early and Repeated Exposure to Examples Improves Creative Work. *Proceedings of the 34th Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (CogSci 2012)*.

N. Abadala, Chinmay Kulkarni, Joseph Joy, Naren Datha, Aditya Sankar, and Rebbecca Walton. 2010. An Interactive Multimedia Framework for Digital Heritage Narratives. *Proceedings of the ACM Multimedia International Conference*, 2010 (Short paper).

Sâsa Tomic, Cristian Perfumo, Chinmay Kulkarni, A Armejach, Osman A. Unsal, Adrian Cristal, Mateo Valero. 2009. EazyHTM— Eager-Lazy Hardware Transactional Memory. *IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MI-CRO)* 2009.

## EXTENDED ABSTRACTS

Julia Cambre, Chinmay Kulkarni, Scott Klemmer. Escaping the Echo Chamber: Ideologically and Geographically Diverse Discussions about Politics *Proceedings of CHI: ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.* (2017) – Late Breaking Work.

Yasmine Kotturi, Andrew Du, Scott Klemmer, Chinmay Kulkarni. How does reciprocity-driven peer review evolve over the long-term? *ACM Learning@Scale Work in Progress* (2017).

Justin Cheng, Chinmay Kulkarni. 2013. Tools for Predicting Drop-off in Large Online Classes. Scott Klemmer., Adjunct Proceedings of CHI: ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2013).

Chinmay Kulkarni, Scott Klemmer. 2011. Automatically adapting web pages to heterogeneous devices. Adjunct Proceedings of CHI: ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (2011).

Chinmay Kulkarni, Santosh Raju, and Raghavendra Udupa. 2010. Memento: unifying content and context to aid webpage re-visitation. Adjunct proceedings of UIST: ACM symposium on User interface software and technology, 2010.

Chinmay Kulkarni, Osman Unsal, Adrian Cristal, Eduard Ayguade, Mateo Valero. 2009. Turbocharging Boosted Transactions: Or How I Learnt to Stop Worrying and Love Longer Transactions. *Proceedings of the PPoPP: ACM symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming 2009.* 

Because workshop papers are sometimes not reviewed with the same rigor as conference submissions, these were not included above. A full list is available at Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=ZDatV6MAAAAJ&hl=en.

SELECTED INVITED TALKS Duolingo Mar 2018

Designing Scalable Learning Experiences

MIT Sep 2017

A Case for a Connected Future of Work and Learning

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Sep 2017

A Case for a Connected Future of Work and Learning

#### Northwestern University

Sep 2017

A Case for a Connected Future of Work and Learning

#### LWMOOC conference

Sep 2017

Invited panelist

#### **Princeton University**

Oct 2016

Learning and Working at Global Scales

#### University of Pittsburgh

Aug 2016

Online Learning Studios for Open-ended Domains

#### Harvard University

Oct 2015

Structuring Peer Interactions for Massive Scale Learning

Discussion Affordances for Natural Collaborative Exchange Talk Series Designing with Diversity: Global conversations to enrich massive education Sept 2015.

Coursera, Inc. Fast feedback in a global classroom

Jun 2014

Google, Inc. Using Google Hangouts for Small Discussions in Massive Online Classes May 2014

Berkeley Institute of Design, UC Berkeley Learning better, and Creating Better Learners in MOOCs Apr 2014

Facebook, Inc. Massively Social Online Education: Peers and Networks in Online Courses

Dec 2013

**EDUCAUSE ELI Focus Seminar** Lessons From Peer Assessment In MOOCs Nov 2013

#### **TEACHING**

Spring 2018: 05-530 Tools for Online Learning - 15 units.

Spring 2017: 05-671 Graduate HCI Project - 15 units: Overall teaching: 4.6/5; Overall course: 4.4/5.

Fall 2016: 05-899/05-499 Special Topics in HCI (Learning with Peers at Massive Scale) - 12 units: Overall teaching: 3.8/5; Overall course: 3.5/5.

Spring 2015: 05-899 Special Topics in HCI (Learning with Peers at Massive Scale) - 12 units: 4.6/5; Overall course: 4.6/5.

#### **MENTORING**

#### Graduate students

- Yasmine Kotturi
- Zheng Yao (co-advised with Bob Kraut)
- Julia Cambre

## PhD Dissertation Committees

Fatima Al-Raisi (LTI; advised by Jaime Carbonell) Shayan Doroudi (CSD; advised

by Emma Brunskill)

#### Undergraduates

Rohan Varma, Sarah Moss (CMU), Ashley Reese (Now at Google), Julie Fortuna (Now at Apple). Kanit (Ham) Wongsuphasawat (Now a PhD student at the University of Washington.)

#### SERVICE External

Demos chair, ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing, 2017

Program Committee, ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing, 2017

Program Committee, ACM Conference on Learning at Scale, 2016

Program Committee, ACM Conference on Learning at Scale, 2015

Reviewer @ CHI 2010-2016, TOCHI 2013-2015, CSCW  $^1$  2012-2015, UIST 2011, DIS 2011 and others

<sup>1</sup>Recognized for excellent reviewing.

Student Volunteer: CSCW 2014, UIST 2012 (Chair), UIST 2011, IUI 2011

With Jeff Bigham and Walter Lasecki, taught a course *Crowdsourcing and Crowd Work* at CHI 2017. Attendees learned how to work with the crowd to enable research and practical applications; and how to bake learning opportunities into crowd work.

#### At CMU

HCI representative at the CMU IRB	2017-
HCI Faculty Awards Nomination Committee	2017-
BHCI re-design committee	2017
HCII PhD admissions committee	2015
METALS admissions committee	2015,2016
BHCI admissions committee	2015

#### Distributed Artifacts

GOOGLE, INC.

PeerStudio for the Global Communication Center I am the lead creator of PeerStudio (www.peerstudio.org), a peer review system for fast, revision-oriented feedback. More than 10,000 students have used it. At CMU, this is the basis of the Global Communication Center's "Leave a Review, Take a Review" system: https://www.cmu.edu/gcc/appointment/cover-letter.html

Talkabout: Small-group discussions in massive classes I am the lead creator of Talkabout (http://talkaboutlearning.in), a small-group real time video discussion system for MOOCs. Over 20,000 students from 135 countries have used it to discuss topics as varied as organizational behavior, psychology, philanthropy, womens health rights, creativity, and designing effective experiments. After the 2016 Presidential Election, we offered it as a platform for public discourse.

PREVIOUS RESEARCH POSITIONS

Research Intern
MICROSOFT RESEARCH INDIA
Research Developer
MICROSOFT RESEARCH
Research Intern
BARCELONA SUPERCOMPUTING CENTER

Mountain View, CA
Summer 2011
Bangalore, India
Oct 2009- Sep 2010
Redmond, WA
Summer 2009
Barcelona, Spain

 ${\bf Research\ Intern} \\ {\bf Intern}$ 

Jan 2009 - May 2009 Summer 2008 SELECTED PRESS

**CNBC** Dec 13, 2016

Post-election therapy across Silicon Valley after Trump win.

**Seeker** Dec 14, 2016

'Mini U.N.' Online Platform Fights the Echo Chamber Effect

EdSurge Mar 4, 2016

Could Slack Be the Next Online Learning Platform?

Stanford Report May 6, 2015

Stanford Researchers Use Diverse, Global Discussion Groups to Boost Online Learning Experience for Participants

Harvard Business Review

April 23, 2014

"The Right Colors Make Data Easier to Read"

EdSurge June 24, 2015

"5 Essential Steps to Building Community for your Online Course"

Financial Times December 9, 2013

"Moocs: Can Free Classes Match an MBA?"